What is love?
ماهو الحب ؟
It's a hard term to define
مصطلح يصعب تعريفه ؟
in so far as it has a very wide application.
وهو مصطلح له تطبيقات واسعة للغاية
I can love jogging.
قد أحب ممارسة رياضة الهرولة
I can love a book, a movie.
أو أحب كتاب، أو فيلم
I can love escalopes.
قد أحب الإسكالوب
I can love my wife.
قد أحب زوجتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But there's a great difference
لكن هناك فرق كبير
between an escalope and my wife, for instance.
بين الأسكالوب وزوجتي
That is, if I value the escalope,
هذا فقط، إذا كنت أقدِّر الإسكالوب
the escalope, on the other hand, it doesn't value me back.
ومن جهة أخرى، فإن الإسكالوب لن يقُدرِّني في المقابل
Whereas my wife, she calls me
بينما وعلى العكس من ذلك، تدعوني زوجتي
the star of her life.
بأني نجم حياتها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Therefore, only another desiring conscience
وبالتالي يمكن لإداراك واعي آخر
can conceive me as a desirable being.
أن يعتبرني ككائن مرغوب فيه
I know this, that's why
أدرك هذا، لكن لماذا؟
love can be defined in a more accurate way
يمكن تعريف الحب بطريقة أكثر تحديداً
as the desire of being desired.
على أنه الرغبة في أن تكون مرغوباً بك
Hence the eternal problem of love:
وبالتالي تنشأ المشكلة الأبدية في موضوع الحب
how to become and remain desirable?
كيف تمسي وتبقى محبوباً
The individual used to find
إعتاد الأفراد على
an answer to this problem
إيجاد جواب لهذه المسألة
by submitting his life to community rules.
عن طريق تكريس حياتهم لقواعد المجتمع
You had a specific part to play
لديك جزء محدد لتلعبه
according to your sex, your age,
طبقاً لجنسك، ولفئتك العمرية
your social status,
وحالتك الإجتماعية
and you only had to play your part
وكل ما عليك هو القيام بدورك
to be valued and loved by the whole community.
ليتم تقديرك وحبك من قبل المُجتمع ككل
Think about the young woman who must remain chaste before marriage.
فكر بالمرأة الشابة التي يتوجب عليها أن تبقى عفيفة قبل الزواج
Think about the youngest son who must obey the eldest son,
فكر بالإبن الأصغر الذي يتوجب عليه إطاعة الإبن الأكبر
who in turn must obey the patriarch.
واللذان يتوجب عليها إطاعة والديهما كذلك
But a phenomenon
لكن هناك ظاهرة
started in the 13th century,
بدأت في القرن 13
mainly in the Renaissance, in the West,
وتحديداً في عصر النهضة، في الغرب
that caused the biggest identity crisis
وتسببت بأكبر أزمة هوية
in the history of humankind.
في تاريخ الإنسانية
This phenomenon is modernity.
هذه الظاهرة هي الحداثة
We can basically summarize it through a triple process.
ويمكننا تلخيصها بعملية ثلاثية
First, a process of rationalization of scientific research,
الأولى، عملية عقلنة البحث العلمي
which has accelerated technical progress.
والتي زادت بدورها من التطور التقني
Next, a process of political democratization,
والثانية، عملية الدمقرطة السياسية
which has fostered individual rights.
والتي عززت من الحقوق الفردية
And finally, a process of rationalization of economic production
وأخيراً، عملية عقلنة الإنتاج الإقتصادي
and of trade liberalization.
وتحرير التجارة
These three intertwined processes
وهذه الإجراءات الثلاث مجتمعة
have completely annihilated
قد قضت بالكامل
all the traditional bearings of Western societies,
على جميع السلوكيات التقليدية في المجتمعات الغربية
with radical consequences for the individual.
التي كان لها آثار راديكالية على الأفراد
Now individuals are free
وللأفراد اليوم مطلق الحرية
to value or disvalue
في تقدير أو عدم تقدير
any attitude, any choice, any object.
أي إتجاه، أو خيار، أو غرض
But as a result, they are themselves confronted
لكن نتيجة لذلك، يجد الأفراد أنفسهم في مواجهة
with this same freedom that others have
نفس هذه الحريات التي يمتلكها الآخرون
to value or disvalue them.
في تقديرهم أو عدم تقديرهم
In other words, my value was once ensured
وبكلمات أخرى، القيمة التي كانت مضمونة لي
by submitting myself to the traditional authorities.
عن طريق تكريس نفسي للسلطات التقليدية
Now it is quoted in the stock exchange.
تم طرحها في سوق البورصة للتداول
On the free market of individual desires,
في السوق الحرة للرغبات الفردية
I negotiate my value every day.
وأنا مضطر للتفاوض على قيمتي بشكل يومي
Hence the anxiety of contemporary man.
ومن هنا يأتي التوتر للإنسان المُعاصر
He is obsessed: "Am I desirable? How desirable?
وتستحوذ عليه فكرة: "هل أنا شخص مرغوب فيه، والى أي مدى؟
How many people are going to love me?"
كم عدد الأشخاص الذين سيحببوني؟
And how does he respond to this anxiety?
وكيف يستجيب لهذا التوتر
Well, by hysterically collecting symbols of desirability.
حسناً، عن طريق جمع دلالات هذه الرغبة بشكل هيستيري
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I call this act of collecting,
أطلق على هذا اسم عملية جمع
along with others, seduction capital.
رأس مال الإغواء، بالإضافة الى أمور أخرى
Indeed, our consumer society
بالطبع، مجتمعاتنا الإستهلاكية
is largely based on seduction capital.
مبنية بشكل واسع على رأس مال الإغواء
It is said about this consumption that our age is materialistic.
ويقال عن هذا الأستهلاك بأن عصرنا هو مادي
But it's not true! We only accumulate objects
لكن هذا ليس صحيحاً، نحن نقوم بمراكمة الأشياء فقط
in order to communicate with other minds.
كي نتمكن من التواصل مع العقول الأخرى
We do it to make them love us, to seduce them.
نفعل ذلك كي نجعلهم يحبوننا، لإغوائهم
Nothing could be less materialistic, or more sentimental,
لا شيء قد يكون أقل مادية، أو أكثر شاعرية
than a teenager buying brand new jeans
من قيام مراهق بشراء بنطلون جينز جديد
and tearing them at the knees,
ومن ثم تمزيقه عند الركبتين
because he wants to please Jennifer.
لأنه يريد إرضاء جينيفر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Consumerism is not materialism.
الإستهلاكية ليست هي المادية
It is rather what is swallowed up
بل ما يتم ابتلاعه
and sacrificed in the name of the god of love,
والتضحية به بإسم إله الحب
or rather in the name of seduction capital.
أو بإسم رأس مال الإغواء
In light of this observation on contemporary love,
وفي ضوء هذه الرؤية للحب المُعاصر
how can we think of love in the years to come?
كيف ستكون نظرتنا للحب في الأعوام القادمة؟
We can envision two hypotheses:
نستطيع تصور فرضيتين:
The first one consists of betting
الأولى تتكون من المُراهنة على
that this process of narcissistic capitalization will intensify.
أن عملية الإستثمار في حُب الذات هذه سوف تتزايد
It is hard to say what shape this intensification will take,
ومن الصعب التكهن بشكل هذا التزايد
because it largely depends
لأنه يعتمد وبشكل كبير
on social and technical innovations,
على الإبتكارات الإجتماعية والتقنية
which are by definition difficult to predict.
والتي يصعب التكهن بها بطبيعة الحال
But we can, for instance,
لكننا نستطيع، على سبيل المثال،
imagine a dating website
تخيل موقع الكتروني للمواعدة
which, a bit like those loyalty points programs,
والذي يشبه نوعاً ما برامج الولاء باستخدام النقاط
uses seduction capital points
حيث تستخدم نقاط رأس مال الإغواء
that vary according to my age, my height/weight ratio,
والتي تتباين حسب العمر، ومعدل الوزن / الطول،
my degree, my salary,
ودرجتي العلمية، وراتبي،
or the number of clicks on my profile.
أو عدد الزيارات الى صفحتي الشخصية
We can also imagine
نستطيع كذلك تصور
a chemical treatment for breakups
مُعالجة كيميائية للإنفصالات
that weakens the feelings of attachment.
التي تُضعف من مشاعر التعلق
By the way, there's a program on MTV already
وبالمناسبة، هناك برنامج على أم تي في
in which seduction teachers
يقوم به مدرسين الإغواء
treat heartache as a disease.
بمعالجة وجع القلب كمرض
These teachers call themselves "pick-up artists."
ويدعو هؤلاء المعلمين أنفسهم "فناني الإلتقاط"
"Artist" in French is easy, it means "artiste."
"فنّان" بالفرنسية سهل، ويعني "فنّان"
"Pick-up" is to pick someone up,
"الإلتقاط" يعني أن تلتقط شخصاً،
but not just any picking up -- it's picking up chicks.
لكنه ليس أي نوع من الإلتقاط -- إنه التقاط الفتيات
So they are artists of picking up chicks.
لذا فهم فنانين في إجتذاب الفتيات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And they call heartache "one-itis."
ويطلقون على وجع القلب اسم " العدوى - واحد"
In English, "itis" is a suffix that signifies infection.
وفي الإنجليزية هذا التعبير هو مقطع لغوي يعني العدوى
One-itis can be translated as "an infection from one."
ويمكن ترجمته على أنه "العدوى من واحد"
It's a bit disgusting. Indeed, for the pick-up artists,
وهو أمر مثير للإشمئزاز. بالطبع بالنسبة لفناني الإلتقاط،
falling in love with someone
أن تقع في حب أحدهم
is a waste of time,
هو مضيعة للوقت
it's squandering your seduction capital,
وهو تبذير لرأسمال الإغواء
so it must be eliminated
بالتالي يتوجب إزالته
like a disease, like an infection.
كأنه مرض، أو عدوى
We can also envision
ويمكننا كذلك تصور
a romantic use of the genome.
استخدام رومانسي لكلمة الجينوم
Everyone would carry it around
حيث يمكن للجميع حمله معهم
and present it like a business card
وتقديمه كبطاقة أعمال
to verify if seduction can progress to reproduction.
للتثبت من أن الإغواء يمكنه أن يتطور الى إعادة الإنتاج
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course, this race for seduction,
بالطبع، هذا السباق نحو الإغواء
like every fierce competition,
مثله كأي مُسابقة شديدة
will create huge disparities in narcissistic satisfaction,
سيخلق تباينات عظيمة في مُستوى الرضى عن النرجسية
and therefore a lot of loneliness and frustration too.
وبالتالي الكثير من الوحدة والإحباط كذلك
So we can expect that modernity itself,
لذا يمكننا أن نتوقع أن الحداثة بذاتها،
which is the origin of seduction capital, would be called into question.
وهي مصدر رأس مال الإغواء يمكن الشك فيها كذلك.
I'm thinking particularly of the reaction
وأنا أفكر بالتحديد في رد الفعل
of neo-fascist or religious communes.
تجاه المجتمعات الفاشية - الجديدة أو المجتمعات الدينية.
But such a future doesn't have to be.
لكن لا يتوجب أن يكون المُستقبل كذلك.
Another path to thinking about love may be possible.
قد يتخذ التفكير بالحب مسلكاً آخر.
But how?
لكن كيف؟
How to renounce the hysterical need to be valued?
كيف ننبذ الحاجة الهيستيرية الى التقدير؟
Well, by becoming aware of my uselessness.
حسناً، عن طريق أن تصبح واعياً لعدم نفعي في الحياة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yes,
نعم،
I'm useless.
أنا بلا نفع.
But rest assured:
لكن إطمئن:
so are you.
وكذلك أنت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We are all useless.
جميعنا بلا فائدة.
This uselessness is easily demonstrated,
ويمكن بيان هذه اللافائدة بسهولة،
because in order to be valued
وذلك أنه كي يتم تقديري
I need another to desire me,
أحتاج شخصاً آخر له رغبة في،
which shows that I do not have any value of my own.
الأمر الذي يظهر على أنه لا قيمة شخصية لي على الإطلاق
I don't have any inherent value.
أي أنني لا أتلك أي قيمة متأصلة بذاتي.
We all pretend to have an idol;
تنظاهر جميعنا بأن لدينا قُدوة أعلى
we all pretend to be an idol for someone else, but actually
تنظاهر جميعنا بأننا قُدوة لشخص آخر، لكن الحقيقة
we are all impostors, a bit like a man on the street
جميعنا مزيفين، مثلنا كرجل في الشارع
who appears totally cool and indifferent,
والذي يبدو بأنه واثق من نفسه وغاية في الهدوء
while he has actually anticipated and calculated
بينما في الحقيقة هو متشوق ومُتحسب
so that all eyes are on him.
بأن كل العيون تراقبه
I think that becoming aware
أظن بأنه لكي نصبح واعيين
of this general imposture
لهذا الموقف العام
that concerns all of us
الذي يهمنا جميعاً
would ease our love relationships.
سوف يخفف من علاقات الحب خاصتنا
It is because I want to be loved
لأنه بسبب أني أريد أن يحبني الآخرون
from head to toe,
من الرأس للقدم
justified in my every choice,
مُبرر في كل خيار من خياراتي
that the seduction hysteria exists.
بأن هسيتيريا الإغواء موجودة بالفعل
And therefore I want to seem perfect
وبالتالي أريد أن أظهر بأني شخص كامل
so that another can love me.
كي يحبني شخص آخر
I want them to be perfect
أريدهم أن يكونوا كاملين
so that I can be reassured of my value.
بحيث أكون مطمئناً على قيمتي الذاتية
It leads to couples
مما يقود الى أزواج
obsessed with performance
مهووسين بالأداء
who will break up, just like that,
والذين سينفصلون عن بعضهم البعض، بكل سهولة
at the slightest underachievement.
عند أدنى فشل
In contrast to this attitude,
بالمقابل
I call upon tenderness -- love as tenderness.
أدعو الى الرِّقة-- الحب كرِّقة
What is tenderness?
ما هي الرِّقة
To be tender is to accept the loved one's weaknesses.
الرِّقة هي أن تقبل نقاط ضعف المحبوب
It's not about becoming a sad couple of orderlies.
وليس في أن تصبحوا زوجين حزنين من الناس المحافظين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's pretty bad.
هذا سيء للغاية
On the contrary,
على النقيض،
there's plenty of charm and happiness in tenderness.
هناك الكثير من السحر والسعادة في الرِّقة
I refer specifically to a kind of humor that is unfortunately underused.
وأشير بالخصوص الى نوع من الفكاهة والتي لسوء الحظ لا تستخدم بشكل كافي
It is a sort of poetry of deliberate awkwardness.
انه كنوع من الشعر الخاص بالغرابة المقصودة
I refer to self-mockery.
أشير الى الإستهزاء - بالذات
For a couple who is no longer sustained, supported
الى زوجين لا يديمهما، أو يسندهما
by the constraints of tradition,
تحديدات التقاليد،
I believe that self-mockery
أؤمن بأن الإستهزاء - بالذات
is one of the best means for the relationship to endure.
هو أحد أفضل السُّبُل لديمومة العلاقات